Guide to the Roone Arledge Papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Roone Arledge Papers,
1953-2002.
Arledge, Roone.
20 linear feet (39 document boxes, 1 large index card box)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library, New York, NY. 10027
MS#1423
6297800
This collection documents the professional career of television executive, Roone Arledge, during his time as President of the News and Sports divisions of the American Broadcasting Company (ABC).
Biographical Note
Roone Pinckney Arledge Jr. was born on July 8, 1931 in Forest Hill,s Queens. His father was a lawyer for equitable Life Insurance and his mother, Gertrude, was a housewife. The family moved to Merrick, Long Island where Arledge attended Mepham High School. Arledge went to Columbia College where he majored in Foreign Affairs, Politics and Government, and the Humanities. During his undergraduate years, he was a member, and eventually president, of Phi Gamma Delta, a member of the Class Steering Committee, and received Gold and Silver King's Crowns for extracurricular leadership. He was also editor of both the Columbian (the yearbook) and The Spectator (the campus newspaper). Arledge attended Columbia from 1948 to 1952; however, he officially graduated in 1954. Arledge also pursued graduate work at the School of International Affairs, Columbia University. He specialized in the Near and Middle East, but did not complete the program.
Arledge first started working in television in December 1952 for the DuMont Television Network. He was the assistant to the Associate Director of Programming and Production. His duties included managing the budget for select shows, paying talent, and general administrative work.
In March of 1953, Arledge was conscripted to the United States Army. There he served as Chief of the Radio and Television Section of the Public Information Office at the Aberdeen Proving Grounds in Maryland. In this role, Arledge distributed information with regard to the United States Army Ordnance Corps, its weapons, training and other relevant issues to local radio stations and television networks. He also produced, directed, and wrote a thrice-weekly radio program. Arledge received a Good Conduct medal in December of 1954 and a National Defense Service Medal. During this time, Arledge married his first wife, Joan Dorothy Heise. They would go on to have four children together: Roone Pinckney, Patricia Lu, Elizabeth Ann, and Susan Lee.
Arledge was hired by NBC in 1954. Shortly after, he was transferred to the Army Reserve. At NBC, Arledge held a variety of positions. He was a stage manager, then unit Supervisor, and finally a staff producer/director. In this last position he produced a children's show entitled Hi Mom, Christmas at Rockefeller Center (featuring Dick Button who was later a commentator for Ice Skating at the ABC covered Olympics), Sunday's Schedule, election night coverage, and travel shows.
Arledge also wrote several shows. Masterpiece dramatized stories on the creation of "high art," such as the Sistine Chapel. A second concept, For Men Only, would feature jazz music and present male-oriented topics. While both shows were unsuccessful, the latter caught the eye of Edgar J. Scherick who ran the sports division for ABC.
In 1960 Arledge joined ABC Sports as a producer of NCAA football games. ABC was in financial trouble and, in terms of ratings, the weakest of the three major stations: ABC, CBS, and NBC. This was an opportune moment to enact change at ABC and throughout his career, Arledge did simply that. One year after being hired, Arledge created ABC's Wide World of Sports, one of the highest rated sports shows in television history. In 1968, Arledge became president of ABC Sports. Under his guidance, ABC Sports grew one of the most well-known and respected broadcasting organizations in the world. Arledge promoted the use of innovative camera techniques such as slow motion, freeze frame, instant replay, split-screen, incorporated underwater cameras during swimming competitions and utilized end zone cameras during football coverage.
In addition to Wide World of Sports, Arledge brought football to primetime, a move that no one had attempted. With NFL Monday Night Football, a new era in sports broadcasting was opened. A key aspect of Arledge's impact was his use of commentators for sporting events. Previously, leagues had the right to approve announcers. Arledge ignored this trend and decided to use Howard Cosell against the views of the league. Along with Cosell, Jim McKay and Frank Gifford became household names as sports announcers. This technique, of using "star" personalities came into play when Arledge moved over to ABC News as well.
Arledge and ABC Sports also presented major golf tournaments, Major League Baseball, championship boxing, the Indianapolis 500, racing, including the Kentucky Derby and ten Olympic Games. He was president of that division until 1986. While at ABC Sports, Arledge divorced his first wife and married Ann Fowler, a former Miss Alabama, in 1976.
On June 1, 1977, in a wave of more unprecedented action, Arledge was named President of ABC News in addition to ABC Sports. In this role, he created the top shows World News Tonight, 20/20, Closeup, and Nightline. He was instrumental in building a team of top journalists and aggressively pursued anchors from other networks. Barbara Walters, Diane Sawyer, Peter Jennings, David Brinkley, and Ted Koppell all worked for Arledge. ABC News represented big names as well as big salaries, another first in the industry. Roone Arledge kept this position for almost ten years and maintained his role as President of ABC News for twenty.
In 1997, David Westin was named President of ABC News and Arledge became Chair. Almost all of Arledge's news shows had received awards and the network itself had received the Alfred I. duPont-Columbia University Award for the overall commitment of excellence, the first time a news organization had been honored in that way. Arledge had won 37 Emmys, including the first life-time achievement Emmy ever granted, the Distinguished Achievement Award from the Journalism Alumni Association, the Grand Prize at the Cannes Film Festival for live television broadcasting, and the Silver Medal of the Olympic Order from the International Olympic Committee. He was quoted as saying his most treasured award was a George Foster Peabody Award--he received a total of four of these awards--given for coverage of the 1972 Olympics in Munich where eleven Israeli athletes were taken hostage and killed. ABC was the only network able to transmit their broadcast out of Germany and link the rest of the world to the tragedy.
Arledge had battled prostate cancer in the last years of his life, conducting business mainly by phone, but nevertheless, staying in the thick of work. He died on November 5, 2002.
Scope and Content
The Roone Arledge Papers consist primarily of office material generated from his time as President of ABC News and ABC Sports. The bulk of the collection is comprised of correspondence, both internal to the corporation and external. Letters were exchanged between Arledge and other top management during all phases of a show: the creation, production, and maintenance. There are also topical files related to the management of the two divisions, such as financial records, program development documents, rating and industry reports, legal records, and trip itineraries for numerous business trips to Europe and Asia.
On a broader level, there are records concerning Arledge's overall career at ABC. These consist of various awards and honors he received, research material on other television networks and stations, articles, and papers from professional organizations that he had been involved with.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in six series.
Series I: General, 1953-2002
Series II: Correspondence, 1954-2002
Subseries II.1: Alphabetical, 1982-2001
Subseries II.2: Chronological, 1954-2002
Series III: ABC News, 1977-2002
Series IV: ABC Sports, 1961-2001
Series V: Photographs, 1984-1994
Series VI: Realia, 1989-1992
Subjects
ABC News.; ABC Sports.; Philip Morris Incorporated.; Arledge, Roone.; Broadcast journalism.; Olympics.; Television and sports.; Television--Production and direction.; Awards; Character dolls; Correspondence; Legal documents; Television journalists--United States.
Access Restrictions
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library Reading Room. Please consult the Rare Book and Manuscript Library for further information.
This collection has no restrictions.
Acquisition
Gigi Shaw Arledge, Gift on March 11, 2003.
- Series I: General, 1953-2002
  This small series contains records with regard to Roone Arledge's career in the television industry as a whole. Within this series are articles about Roone Arledge, ABC NEWS, and ABC Sports, various awards Arledge received for his contributions to the field of broadcasting, personal records, such as his diploma from Columbia College and his military records, and speeches that he gave. There are also records pertaining to other news organizations in the United States, Europe, England, and Japan. Arledge was a board member of ESPN and A & E Television Networks and documents concerning his work for them may be found here as well.
  - Articles
    - 1976, (2 Folders) (Box 1, Folder 1 to 2)
    - 1977 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 1978, (2 Folders) (Box 1, Folder 4 to 5)
    - 1979 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 1980 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - 1981-2001 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Awards
    - Alexander Hamilton Medal, 1998 November 18 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Boston University Honorary Degree, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Center for Communication, Inc., 1996-1997 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - George Foster Peabody Broadcasting Award, 1976, 1984 (Folder 14-L-1)
    - International Radio and Television Society, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - The National Academy of Television Arts and Sciences (Emmy Awards), 1979-2002 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - National Press Foundation, 1990-1991 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - The New York State Broadcasters Association, Inc., 2001 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - News World Lifetime Achievement Award, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Olympics, 1980-1988 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Pete Rozelle Radio-Television Award, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - The Radio and Television News Directors Foundation, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - The Television Academy Hall of Fame, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Walter Cronkite Award, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Canadian Embassy Dinner, [1983] (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Carter, Jimmy, 1993-2002 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Certificates, 1969-1977 (Folder 14-L-1)
  - Columbia University Diploma, 1954 February 24 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Council on Foreign Relations
    - General, 2000-2002, (4 Folders) (Box 3, Folder 1 to 4)
    - Committee on Corporate Affairs and Development, 2000-2002 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Committee on Meetings and Media Projects, 1997-2002 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Delegation to Turkey and Israel, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - International Advisory Board, 1998-2000 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - House Sub-Committee on Telecommunications Testimony, 1987-1989 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Interviews, undated, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - John Kennedy School of Government, 1998-2002, (3 Folders) (Box 4, Folder 5 to 7)
  - Memoirs, 1984-2002 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center, 1987-2000 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Military Records, 1953-1955 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - The Museum of Television and Radio, 1993-1994 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - News Organizations
    - BBC--General, 1993-2001, (4 Folders) (Box 5, Folder 5 to 8)
    - BBC--Employees, 1997 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - British Sky Broadcasting, 1991-1994 (Box 6, Folder 2 to 3)
    - Canal Plus, 1991-1993 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - CNN, 1996-1998 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Fox Broadcasting, 1991-1994 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Fujisankei Communications International, Inc., 1999-2000 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Independent Television News Ltd., 1992-1999 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Nine Network Australia Limited, 1991-1994 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Nippon Hoso Kyokai, 1991-1995 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Reuters, 1993-1996 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Non-ABC Professional Work--A & E Television Networks Management Committee, 1998-2002, (2 Folders) (Box 7, Folder 2 to 3)
  - Non-ABC Professional Work--ESPN, 2001-2002, (2 Folders) (Box 7, Folder 4 to 5)
  - Resume, 1954-1960 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Speeches
    - General, 1996-2001 (Box 7)
    - Wake Forest University, 1988 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Wake Forest University--Poster, 1988 September 8 (Box 8, Folder 14-l-1)
  - Trips
    - German Television, 1992-2001 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Nicklaus/Flick Golf School, 1995-1996 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Royal and Ancient Golf Club of St. Andrews, 1991-1999 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Washington Press Club Dinner, 1995 (Box 8, Folder 5)
- Series II: Correspondence, 1954-2002
  Series II is the largest of the collection. The letters held here date from Roone Arledge's time at ABC as head of both the sports and news division. In general, the correspondence, while large in bulk, is limited in content. The letters consist primarily of the type of letters an executive would be professionally obligated to send, such as congratulatory notes to colleagues within and outside of the company, thank you letters for corporate gifts, letters of inquiry from individuals wanting to work at ABC, and complaints from all manners of citizens. This series is divided into two subseries: Topical and Chronological. Please note that individuals listed in Subseries II.1 may be found in Subseries II.2.
  - Subseries II.1: Alphabetical, 1982-2001
    Subseries II.1 is arranged alphabetical by an individual's last name or by topic. Letters listed by a name may be correspondence exchanged to and from that person or about that person. These individuals are mainly other ABC senior executives and administrative staff as well as numerous anchors. Notable individuals include Peter Jennings, Barbara Walter, Diane Sawyer, Ted Koppel, and Robert Iger.
    - Baker, Barry, 1997 July (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Cosell, Howard, 1982 December-1985 April (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Downs, Hugh, 1992 August-1998 January (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Friedman, Paul, 1991 August-1993 October (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Goodman, Roger, 1990 March-1994 July (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Granum, Rex, 1995 September-1996 December (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Iger, Robert, 1994 March-1998 August (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - International Radio and Television Society Award, 1982 November-1983 March (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Jennings, Peter, 1991 September-2001 February (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - Kipper, Judith, 1991 July-1998 February (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Koppel, Ted, 1988 August-1996 April (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Nine Sundays, 1991 September (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - O'Neil, Terry, 1994 August-1996 February (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Patterson, Neil, 1997 September-1999 May (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Personal, 1981 August-1994 January, (2 Folders) (Box 9, Folder 6 to 7)
    - Sawyer, Diane, 1989 February-2000 March (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Sawyer, Forrest, 1993 February-1997 August (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Sias, John, 1990 December-1991 February (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Stossel, John, 1992 June-1995 February (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Temple, Bill, 1996 January-1997 March (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Wald, Richard, 1993 December-1999 November, (2 Folders) (Box 10, Folder 3 to 4)
    - Walters, Barbara, 1987 March-1999 January (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Westin, David, 1994 October-2000 August (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Zucker, John, 1994 October-1997 July (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Subseries II.2: Chronological, 1954-2002
    The correspondence contained in this subseries is primarily external. The majority of the letters are requests for Arledge to research certain topics for potential inclusion in one of ABC's news shows, attend fundraising functions, accept ideas for new shows, or participate in a conference or lecture series. There are also complaints from viewers and, to a lesser extent, complimentary letters. The interoffice correspondence consists of lengthy memos, many of which have multiple notes written on them from different senior executives.
    - Incoming
      - 1976 February-1981 December (Box 11, Folder 1)
      - 1984 January-December, (2 Folders) (Box 11, Folder 2 to 3)
      - 1985
        - January-March (Box 11, Folder 4)
        - March-May (Box 11, Folder 5)
        - June-September (Box 11, Folder 6)
        - September-December (Box 11, Folder 7)
      - 1986 January-September (Box 12, Folder 1)
      - 1986 April-1987 May (Box 12, Folder 2)
      - 1986 July-December (Box 12, Folder 3)
      - 1988 January-July (Box 12, Folder 4)
      - 1988 August-December (Box 12, Folder 5)
      - Memos, 1989 January-September (Box 13, Folder 1)
      - Memos, 1989 October-December (Box 13, Folder 2)
      - 1989 January-September (Box 13, Folder 3)
      - 1989 October-December (Box 13, Folder 4)
      - Memos, 1990 January-June (Box 13, Folder 5)
      - Memos, 1990 July-December (Box 13, Folder 6)
      - 1990
        - January-February (Box 14, Folder 1)
        - March-April (Box 14, Folder 2)
        - June-September (Box 14, Folder 3)
        - October-December (Box 14, Folder 4)
      - Memos, 1991 January-May (Box 14, Folder 5)
      - Memos, 1991 July-September (Box 14, Folder 6)
      - 1991 January-June (Box 15, Folder 1)
      - 1991 October-December (Box 15, Folder 2)
      - Memos, 1992 February-September (Box 15, Folder 3)
      - 1992 January-June (Box 15, Folder 4)
      - 1992 July-November (Box 15, Folder 5)
      - Memos, 1993-1998 (Box 15, Folder 6)
      - 1993 January-November (Box 15, Folder 7)
      - 1994 January-December (Box 16, Folder 1)
      - 1995 January-August (Box 16, Folder 2)
      - 1995 September-December (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - Outgoing
      - 1954 January-1961 June (Box 16, Folder 4)
      - Memos, 1978 October-1983 June (Box 16, Folder 5)
      - Memos, 1984 February-1987 December (Box 16, Folder 6)
      - 1984 January-May (Box 16, Folder 7)
      - 1984 June-August (Box 17, Folder 1)
      - 1984 September-December (Box 17, Folder 2)
      - 1985 January-April (Box 17, Folder 3)
      - 1985 Mary-September (Box 17, Folder 4)
      - 1985 October-December (Box 17, Folder 5)
      - 1986 January-June (Box 17, Folder 6)
      - 1986 July-December (Box 17, Folder 7)
      - 1987 January-June (Box 18, Folder 1)
      - 1987 July-December (Box 18, Folder 2)
      - Memos, 1988 June-December (Box 18, Folder 3)
      - 1988 February-July (Box 18, Folder 4)
      - 1988 August-November (Box 18, Folder 5)
      - Memos, 1989 January-December (Box 18, Folder 6)
      - 1989 July-October (Box 18, Folder 7)
      - Memos, 1990 April-August (Box 18, Folder 8)
      - 1990 May-December (Box 18, Folder 9)
      - Memos, 1991 April-June (Box 19, Folder 1)
      - 1991 January-July (Box 19, Folder 2)
      - 1991 August-December (Box 19, Folder 3)
      - Memos, 1992 January-December (Box 19, Folder 4)
      - 1992 January-April (Box 19, Folder 5)
      - 1992 June-December (Box 19, Folder 6)
      - 1993 January-December (Box 19, Folder 7)
      - 1994 January-September (Box 19, Folder 8)
      - 1994 October-December (Box 20, Folder 1)
      - 1995 January-December (Box 20, Folder 2)
      - 1996 January-June (Box 20, Folder 3)
      - 1996 July-December (Box 20, Folder 4)
      - Memos, 1997-2000 (Box 20, Folder 5)
      - 1997 January-December (Box 20, Folder 6)
      - 1998 January-1999 February (Box 21, Folder 1)
    - Incoming and Outgoing, 1997 January-1999 November, (2 Folders) (Box 21, Folder 2 to 3)
    - Incoming and Outgoing, 2000 January-2002 August, (2 Folders) (Box 21, Folder 4 to 5)
- Series III: ABC News, 1977-2002
  Series III is comprised of topical files documenting Roone Arledge's time as President of ABC News. Included are financial records, such as operating budgets and long range plans, program development for potential news shows, legal documents from several lawsuits, concerning predominantly the Food Lion and Philip Morris cases, and documents in regards to various trips Arledge conducted. Of note are Arledge's appointment books that were maintained by his personal assistant. These books contain Arledge's numerous appointments, meetings, trips and other activities related to his work at ABC. Often, names of individuals who participated in these activities are listed as well. The notebooks provide insight into how Arledge organized his time as well as show the amount of coordination involved in being President of ABC News.
  - ABC Affiliate News Director Advisory Board, 1994-1998 (Box 21, Folder 6)
  - Anchors, 1988-2000 (Box 21, Folder 7)
  - AOL Merger, 1996-1997 (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - Appointment Books
    - 1977 (Box 22, Folder 2)
    - 1978 (Box 22, Folder 3)
    - 1979 (Box 22, Folder 4)
    - 1980 (Box 22, Folder 5)
    - 1981 (Box 22, Folder 6)
    - 1982 (Box 22, Folder 7)
    - 1983 (Box 23, Folder 1)
    - 1983 (Box 23, Folder 2)
    - 1984 (Box 23, Folder 3)
    - 1985 (Box 23, Folder 4)
    - 1986 (Box 23, Folder 5)
    - 1987 (Box 23, Folder 6)
    - 1988 (Box 24, Folder 1)
    - 1988 (Box 24, Folder 2)
    - 1989 (Box 24, Folder 3)
    - 1990 (Box 24, Folder 4)
    - 1991 (Box 24, Folder 5)
    - 1992 (Box 24, Folder 6)
    - 1993 (Box 25, Folder 1)
    - 1993 (Box 25, Folder 2)
    - 1994 (Box 25, Folder 3)
    - 1995 (Box 25, Folder 4)
    - 1996 (Box 25, Folder 6)
    - 1997 (Box 25, Folder 7)
    - 1998 (Box 26, Folder 1)
    - 1999 (Box 26, Folder 2)
    - 2000 (Box 26, Folder 3)
    - 2001 (Box 26, Folder 4)
    - 2002 (Box 26, Folder 5)
  - Finances
    - 5-Year Plan, 1996 (Box 26, Folder 6)
    - Forecast, 1998 (Box 26, Folder 7)
    - Forecast, 1999 (Box 27, Folder 1)
    - Long Range Plan, 1995-1996 (Box 27, Folder 2)
    - Long Range Plan, 1998 (Box 27, Folder 3)
    - Operating Budget, 1998 (Box 27, Folder 4)
    - Operating Budget, 1999 (Box 27, Folder 5)
  - Government, 1979-1980 (Box 27, Folder 6)
  - Gulf War, 1991 (Box 28, Folder 1)
  - Investigative Team, 1998 (Box 28, Folder 2)
  - Lawsuits
    - General, 1994-1995 (Box 28, Folder 3)
    - Food Lion, 1996-1997 (Box 28, Folder 4)
    - Philip Morris
      - Articles (Box 28, Folder 5)
      - Call Registers
        - 1992 August 12 (Box 28, Folder 6)
        - 1992 October-December (Box 28, Folder 7)
        - 1992 December-1993 February (Box 28, Folder 8)
        - 1992 December-1994 January (Box 29, Folder 1)
        - 1993 February-April (Box 29, Folder 2)
        - 1993 April-June (Box 29, Folder 3)
        - 1993 June-August (Box 29, Folder 4)
        - 1993 August-October (Box 29, Folder 5)
        - 1993 November-1994 January (Box 29, Folder 6)
        - 1994 January-1995 January (Box 29, Folder 7)
        - 1994 January-March (Box 29, Folder 8)
        - 1994 March-May (Box 29, Folder 9)
        - 1994 May-July (Box 30, Folder 1)
        - Undated (Box 30, Folder 2)
      - Correspondence, 1994 August-1995 August (Box 30, Folder 3)
      - Press Releases, 1995 (Box 30, Folder 4)
      - Transcripts (Box 30, Folder 5)
  - National Town Meeting, 1991-1993 (Box 30, Folder 6)
  - NewsOne, 1986-1994 (Box 30, Folder 7)
  - NewsWorld, 1999-2000 (Box 30, Folder 8)
  - Notebooks, undated (Box 30, Folder 9)
  - Political Coverage--General, 1978-1992, (2 Folders) (Box 31, Folder 1 to 2)
  - Political Coverage--Cheney, Dick, 1991 (Box 31, Folder 3)
  - Program Development
    - General, 1987-1992, (2 Folders) (Box 31, Folder 4 to 5)
    - 24-Hour News, 1996, (2 Folders) (Box 31, Folder 6 to 7)
    - Moments of Crisis, 1992-1993 (Box 32, Folder 1)
    - Saturday Shows, 1997-1998 (Box 32, Folder 2)